<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A second letter to his honoured friend Mr. M.T. one of the committee chosen by the Common-Council of London for the insuring of houses from fire</title>
            <author>L. R.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58193</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R42</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R213591</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825933</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825933</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30325</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58193)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30325)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2055:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A second letter to his honoured friend Mr. M.T. one of the committee chosen by the Common-Council of London for the insuring of houses from fire</title>
                  <author>L. R.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: L.R.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Publication date suggested by Wing. Part of a controversy between the City of London and the Insurance Office for Houses; related documents are dated late 1681.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Insurance Office for Houses (London, England) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>City of London (England). --  Court of Common Council --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Insurance, Fire --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:30325:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Second LETTER to his Honoured Friend Mr. <hi>M. T.</hi> one of the Committee choſen by the <hi>Common-Council</hi> of <hi>London</hi> for the <hi>Inſuring</hi> of Houſes from <hi>Fire.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Paper which you ſent me, publiſh't by <hi>the Gentlemen of the Inſurance Office behind the Royal Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> Entituled, <hi>Obſervations on the Propoſals of the City to Inſure Houſes in caſe of Fire,</hi> I have received, and carefully peruſed; and ſhall here return you ſome <hi>Reflections</hi> upon it, which I doubt not will be kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accepted by you, becauſe the deſign of this Paper is the ſame with that of your Counſels, <hi>viz.</hi> the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting the Publick Advantage of your City. I have ſpent ſome time in enquiring who were the <hi>firſt Inventors</hi> of this deſign of <hi>Inſuring Houſes,</hi> becauſe I find theſe Gentlemen do with a great deal of confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence aſcribe it to themſelves in all thoſe ſeveral Pamphlets, which have been <hi>ſcatter'd</hi> (like their <hi>Brains</hi>) and ſo indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriouſly ſpread abroad by them; and eſpecially in this, in almoſt every Paragraph of it, which I have now under Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination. But herein they have done juſt as if a man ſhould <hi>filch</hi> away a piece of Plate from his Neighbour, and ſetting his own Mark upon it, ſhould impudently vouch himſelf to be the right and lawful owner of it. For I find this deſign was firſt ſet on foot immediately after his <hi>Majeſties</hi> Reſtauration by ſeveral <hi>Perſons of Quality, and Eminent Citizens of London,</hi> and <hi>Propoſals</hi> about it then printed by them. But tho the Project and the Authors of it were then recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the <hi>Common Council</hi> of <hi>London</hi> by his <hi>Majeſties</hi> Letter, yet it was not admitted by them, for the very ſame reaſon for which <hi>theſe Gentlemen</hi> now are not to be countenanced in it; <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe they thought it impoſſible for private Perſons to manage, and unreaſonable that <hi>they</hi> (and not the City) ſhould reap the Profits of ſuch an undertaking. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon this Deſign, like ſome Rivers that ſink down into the Ground, and break not out again, but at a conſiderable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, was no more heard of till the Year 1670. when it was afreſh propounded to the City by Mr. <hi>De Laun,</hi> tho not proſecuted by them. However in the Majoralty of Sir <hi>W. Hooker</hi> it was briskly revived by Mr. <hi>Newbold</hi> the <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant,</hi> who propoſed the carrying it on by a <hi>Joint-Stock</hi> to be rais'd among the Inhabitants and Proprietors of the Houſes to be Inſured. This he communicated to the <hi>Lord Mayor,</hi> and divers <hi>other eminent Citizens.</hi> From ſome of theſe, like an <hi>Eves-dropper, this Obſervator</hi> caught it; it being then generally diſcours'd and approv'd of, and reſolv'd to be put in practice. Accordingly Sir <hi>Robert Viner</hi> being choſen <hi>Lord Mayor</hi> for the then enſuing Year, Mr. <hi>Newbold</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd Mr. <hi>Moſyer</hi> as his <hi>Chief Council</hi> in order to preſent it to the City, and gave him a Fee of above four pound. But ſtill the hands of the City were ſo full of other buſineſs, that tho they had a ſtrong Inclination, yet they had no leiſure to carry on this Deſign. Mr. <hi>Newbold</hi> therefore waiting for a more favourable Conjunction, found it not till the Major<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty of Sir <hi>Robert Clayton,</hi> to whom on <hi>New-years-day, Anno</hi> 7 8/9, he preſented the Model of it; and ſometime after prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it under the Title of <hi>London's Improvement, and the Builder's Security, &amp;c.</hi> and preſented it to ſeveral <hi>Aldermen, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Council-men,</hi> and other Eminent Citizens. Sir <hi>Robert Clayton</hi> approved of the matter; only adviſed that inſtead of a <hi>Joint-Stock</hi> it ſhould be managed by the <hi>Chamber</hi> of <hi>London.</hi> And the ſame was the Year following by Sir <hi>Patience Ward,</hi> then <hi>Lord Mayor,</hi> tendred to the <hi>Common-Council.</hi> By them it was referr'd to a <hi>Committee,</hi> who after 8 Months time brought in their <hi>Report,</hi> That <hi>the thing was very well worthy the City's proſecution.</hi> And again, on the 15 of <hi>October</hi> they brought in another <hi>Report</hi> confirming the former. Whereupon the <hi>Common-Council</hi> immediately voted and agreed That the <hi>City ſhould undertake it.</hi> The 15 of <hi>Nov.</hi> following, the <hi>Committee</hi> brought in their <hi>Propoſals</hi> to the <hi>Common-Council,</hi> who conſented to them, and order'd that <hi>the matter ſhould be ſpeedily put in execution.</hi> Thus you ſee, Sir, this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign was <hi>firſt</hi> ſtarted about the Year 1660. renew'd <hi>An.</hi> 1670. revived again by Mr. <hi>Newbold</hi> in 1674. and proſecuted by him (tho with but little ſucceſs for the reaſon above-mentioned) till 1679; and from that time to this day follow'd with greater vigour, and to better purpoſe. Now after Mr. <hi>Newbold</hi> had for ſeveral years been puſhing forward this Deſign by propoſing a <hi>Joint-Stock of</hi> 50000 <hi>Pounds to be raiſed among the Inhabitants and Proprietors of</hi> 4000 <hi>Houſes of the New-Brick-Buildings at</hi> 5 <hi>per Cent. on their value;</hi> (each Houſe being reckon'd at 250 Pounds value one with another) Nay, <hi>after</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Clayton</hi> had, inſtead of this <hi>Joint-Stock,</hi> propoſed that <hi>the City ſhould manage it by ſetling a Fund of their own to that value</hi> (which in truth makes no eſſential difference, only gives a much better Security to the Inſured) <hi>After</hi> this, I ſay, theſe <hi>Private Gentlemen</hi> ſtart up and propoſe the ſetling of <hi>Ground-Rents and Lands to the value of but</hi> 30000 <hi>Pounds for the Inſuring of</hi> 3000 <hi>Houſes, at an annual Rent for</hi> 31 <hi>years only, the profit to themſelves;</hi> whereas the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Propoſal of Mr. <hi>Newbold</hi> was intended to be perpetual, and the improvement of the <hi>Joint-Stock</hi> to be from time to time divided amongſt the Inſured that raiſed it. With what reaſon or modeſty therefore they can pretend to be the <hi>firſt Inventors</hi> of this good Deſign, let the World judge; eſpecially when they themſelves will confeſs that two years a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go they had no thought at all of undertaking it. I think 'tis very plain, that in this matter they have done like ſome <hi>Beggars,</hi> who borrow other mens Children to carry about with them as a Stratagem to get money by.</p>
            <p>But if they cannot make good their Charge of <hi>Injuſtice</hi> againſt you for <hi>Robbing</hi> them of <hi>their Invention,</hi> they will endeavour to have you condemn'd as guilty of <hi>Imprudence</hi> in the managing of it. To which purpoſe <hi>this Obſervator</hi> hath exhibited Four Articles againſt you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He accuſes <hi>your taking Subſcriptions as a thing vain and needleſs: For</hi> (ſays he) <hi>there can be no occaſion for them, but only to ſee whether this Deſign</hi> (being altogether new) <hi>would be approved of. But this is plain already, that it does give gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſatisfaction. Therefore there was no neceſſity of your taking Subſcriptions.</hi> But to this I anſwer, that <hi>taking Subſcriptions</hi> was neceſſary upon another account, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Perſons that do ſubſcribe may chooſe Truſtees from among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon whom the Fund provided for their Security is to be ſetled.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>why ſhould men ſubſcribe to you, when probably it may be ſo long (if ever) before the City ſettle their Fund, that their Houſes may be burnt down before they are Inſured?</hi> To this I anſwer, The Lands and Ground-Rents to the value propoſed are already agreed upon by the City, and a <hi>Draught</hi> of the <hi>Conveyance</hi> is made, and now before Counſel for their Approbation; and 'tis not doubted but the matter will be perfected in a very ſhort time.</p>
            <p>But again (ſaith he) <hi>why ſhould men ſubſcribe to you? For they may come and Inſure at our Office, which is already ſetled, and be releas'd, when they find the City hath made better Proviſion for them.</hi> But I anſwer, The Queſtion will be, Who ſhall be Judge in this caſe, whether the City have made better Proviſion or no? To be ſure theſe Gentlemen will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver confeſs it, be it never ſo plain, who pretend ſo confidently in their <hi>Enquiry, Letter,</hi> and <hi>theſe Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> &amp;c. to demonſtrate that the <hi>City</hi> cannot give ſo good a Security, as they have already. They will hardly be ſo
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:30325:2"/>good natur'd as to let go thoſe Fiſhes which they have once caught in their Nets. They are very forward to take mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney upon almoſt any terms, as <hi>Spunges ſuck up</hi> Water; but the many Suits that are every Term between them and their Creditors, who are at ſo much trouble and charge to recover their own, plainly ſhew 'tis very hard to <hi>wring and ſqueeze it out again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He accuſes you for <hi>ſetting your Rates or Praemiums for Inſuring of Brick Houſes at</hi> 48 <hi>ſhillings</hi> per Cent. <hi>for</hi> 31 <hi>years (and double the price for Timber-Houſes) and ſo in proportion for a longer or a ſhorter time; becauſe this is</hi> 2 <hi>ſhillings</hi> per Cent. <hi>cheaper than theirs.</hi> And declares in requital, That <hi>they will ſink their Prices</hi> 2 <hi>ſhillings and</hi> 2 <hi>pence</hi> per Cent. <hi>lower than yours,</hi> viz. <hi>to</hi> 45 <hi>ſhillings</hi> 10 <hi>pence</hi> per Cent. <hi>for Brick-Houſes for</hi> 31 <hi>years (and double the price for Timber)</hi> and declares <hi>they will always ſet their Prices under the City; tho at preſent they will abate no more unleſs the City does.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I anſwer
<list>
                  <item>(1) They would have cavill'd at the City, let your Prices have been what they would. Had your Rates been <hi>higher</hi> than theirs, then they would have ſaid men might Inſure cheaper with them. Had they been <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual,</hi> then they would have made a noiſe and clamour, that 'twas a <hi>following their Pattern.</hi> And now they are <hi>lower,</hi> they ſlander it as a <hi>contrivance to draw in Cuſtomers.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>(2.) Theſe Gentlemen would have carv'd very fairly for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, had they proceeded according to their <hi>first Propoſals,</hi> who ſtill hope for very conſiderable Gains by this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign (or elſe they would never continue to proſecute it) tho now they will be content with <hi>above</hi> 4 <hi>ſhillings per Cent. leſs</hi> than what they at <hi>firſt</hi> propounded to themſelves. But thus the fierceſt Element by conteſting with its contrary, is made far more <hi>moderate,</hi> than otherwiſe it would have been.</item>
                  <item>(3.) Tho now they have ſet their Rates lower than yours, yet this will be no inducement at all to any wiſe man to Inſure with them, becauſe the <hi>Security</hi> which they give is nothing near ſo good as that which the <hi>City</hi> offers to the Inſured.</item>
               </list>
This I ſhall demonſtrate thus.</p>
            <p>They propoſe to Inſure 3000 Houſes with a Fund of but 30000 Pound value. Now ſuch a Fund can be Security for no more than 150 Houſes, and all that Inſure with them above this number, have no <hi>Security</hi> at all; Nay, even thoſe 150 Houſes too can be enſured to be rebuilt but once neither, tho they pretend to rebuild them as often as they ſhall be burnt in 31 years. For ſhould thoſe 150 Houſes be burnt down, the Rebuilding of them (tho but once) if you rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon them at but 200 pounds <hi>per</hi> Houſe one with another (which I am ſure is low enough) will amount to the juſt ſum of their Fund, which is 30000 pounds. Now ſuppoſe that 12 Houſes be burnt one year, at the rate of 200 pounds for rebuilding each Houſe, there's 2400 pound gone: Suppoſe 12 Houſes be burnt the next year, there's 2400 pounds more gone; and ſo in leſs than 13 years time their whole Fund of 30000 pound muſt be ſpent to ſatisfie the Loſs: Nay, conſidering the Charges they are at in maintaining men for the Quenching of Fires, as they pretend, (tho be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing arm'd <hi>Cap a Pe,</hi> they look as if they were deſign'd to encounter <hi>another Enemy</hi> than the <hi>Fire,</hi> eſpecially if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that none can be employed in that Service within the City, unleſs allowed by Authority) and other matters rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to their Office, which they themſelves Calculate at a 1000 pound <hi>per Annum;</hi> conſidering this, I ſay, their Fund will be gone ſome years ſooner: and then where is the Security for thoſe 150 Houſes the remaining 18 years, or for any of the other Houſes above 150 all the time? If you Reply, <hi>They will not pay the Loſſes for the Houſes that are burnt, out of the Fund, but out of a Bank which they will always have lying ready by them.</hi> I ask how <hi>Private</hi> men, and Perſons ſo much <hi>in Debt</hi> ſhould come by ſuch a Bank, whenas they have expreſly covenanted to put up the yearly Profits of their Fund in their own Pockets? And ſo they had need; for how ſhould they live elſe? For if they had any other Eſtate beſides their Fund, it might reaſonably be preſumed they would pay their <hi>Debts</hi> with it, which yet they have not diſcharged. And if they had not, yet the yearly Profits of their Fund, if they had ſetled as large an one as they at firſt promiſed, amounts but to 2000 pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> (though by the way, what they have ſetled riſes but to 1400 pound <hi>per Annum,</hi> and we may well think they could reach to no more) which will not rebuild above 10 Houſes, if they ſhould be burnt, reckoning them but at 200 pound each Houſe. If you ſay The <hi>Praemiums of the</hi> 150 <hi>Houſes ſhall be laid out to buy more Lands for the Inſuring others,</hi> or <hi>help make up the Loſs.</hi> I anſwer that the <hi>Praemiums</hi> of 150 Houſes inſured for 31 years, reckoning each Houſe at 200 pound value, makes but 750 pound, which is an inconſiderable Sum, and will purchaſe but a few Inches of Ground. If you ſay <hi>the Praemiums of the other Houſes above the</hi> 150 <hi>that are Inſured, ſhall be laid out to buy a further Fund, or help make up the Loſs:</hi> I anſwer, (1.) Why ſhould they have the <hi>Praemiums</hi> of 2850 Houſes for which they can give no other Security but thoſe <hi>Praemiums</hi> themſelves? And (2.) Thoſe <hi>Praemiums</hi> are otherwiſe to be diſpoſed of by them, <hi>viz.</hi> either to buy Ground-Rents or Lands (as far as they will go) for the Inſuring at the <hi>Inns of Court, Chancery,</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſtor;</hi> the Inſuring of which places they pretend they reſolve ſpeedily to undertake. Or elſe (which is more probable) theſe <hi>Praemiums</hi> will be ſlipt into their own Pockets, for their own Private occaſions, which are great enough.</p>
            <p>Beſides, it would be worth enquiring, whether the Lands of a man, liable to a <hi>Statute</hi> of <hi>Bankrupt</hi> 3 years ago, can now be a ſufficient Security? or, (as I intimated in my other Letter) the Lands or Ground-Rents of another, who is (every day) liable to be called to an Account for Male-Adminiſtration in a Publick Office, and which if he ſhould be found to be in Arrears to his Majeſty, would be unavoidably ſeized in his Majeſties behalf. But now if men Inſure with the <hi>City,</hi> the Caſe is quite otherwiſe: For you have a Fund of an 100000 pounds value, which is Security for the Rebuilding of 500 Houſes, reckoning each Houſe as before, at 200 pounds one with another. Then there's the <hi>Praemiums</hi> of thoſe 500 Houſes, and all the reſt which ſhall be Inſured that will be ſetled as an Additional Fund. And laſtly, there is the Annual Rent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> your Original Fund which amounts to 5000 pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> and the Intereſt of the <hi>Praemiums</hi> (which will riſe very high too) both which will be laid by in a Bank by the City (you having no need, as <hi>Private</hi> men have, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply them to any other Purpoſes) Which yearly Revenues will be ſo great as alway to make good all thoſe Loſſes by Fire, which in all probability can happen in any one year; and ſo neither your <hi>Original</hi> nor <hi>Additional Fund</hi> will be diminiſht to make ſatisfaction. Were this but throughly weigh'd, I believe there is none would Inſure with theſe Private men; but they would want <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> as much as they do either <hi>Credit</hi> or <hi>Mony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But further they object, <hi>Our Rates are lower than the Cities, becauſe we Diſcount by way of Purchaſe,</hi> 5 <hi>years paid down for</hi> 8 <hi>years Inſurance;</hi> 7 <hi>for</hi> 12; 9 <hi>and a half for</hi> 21; <hi>and</hi> 11 <hi>for</hi> 31 <hi>years.</hi> Whereas <hi>Your Table is after the Rate of</hi> 13 <hi>years Purchaſe for</hi> 31 <hi>years, and near</hi> 16 <hi>years Purchaſe for</hi> 51: <hi>Prices never heard of among Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwer,
<list>
                  <item>(1.) How low ſoever their Rates are, yet it can be no temptation to any man that under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands himſelf or them, to Inſure at their Office, unleſs <hi>their Security</hi> were better than I have juſt now ſhewn it to be.</item>
                  <item>(2.) Tho this Obſervator pretends, That <hi>your Prices are ſuch as were never heard of among Purchaſers,</hi> yet I am ſure that near 13 years Purchaſe paid down for 31 years, and near 16 for 51 years, are the juſt Prices at <hi>Simple Intereſt</hi> at 5 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr>
                     <hi>per Cent. Rebate,</hi> as it hath been computed by, and atteſted under the hands of two of the moſt exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite Arithmeticians this day in <hi>London.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:30325:2"/>
            <p>Again, ſaith the Obſervator, <hi>If we loſe by this Deſign, we loſe but our own and do no injury to any. But if your Committee loſe by it, they prejudice the whole Body of the Citizens by waſting the Publick Revenues; which are very low already, as appears by the Cities borrowing Mony upon Intereſt, when no viſible improvement is made by it; and by your late raiſing the</hi> Fifteens <hi>to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair the Publick works of the City.</hi> To all which I reply,
<list>
                  <item>(1.) There's no room for this Objection, becauſe 'tis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded on all hands, that this deſign will be Advantagious more or leſs to the Undertakers.</item>
                  <item>(2.) If it were not, the City is not ſo likely to loſe by this deſign as theſe Private Gentlemen, becauſe the <hi>Annual Rents</hi> of your <hi>Original Fund</hi> (not to inſiſt on the Intereſt of the <hi>Praemiums</hi>) are ſo great, that they will at preſent make ſatisfaction for almoſt four times the loſs as theirs will, without reſorting to the <hi>Fund</hi> it ſelf, and the yearly Rents of it being laid by, in a ſhort time will make ſatisfaction for many more times the loſs than theirs will.</item>
                  <item>(3.) What your <hi>Committee</hi> do in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is with the conſent and Approbation of the <hi>whole Common Council,</hi> who being choſen by the Body of the Citizens, are their true <hi>Repreſentatives.</hi> And therefore if the City ſhould be a Loſer by this Deſign, your Committee cannot juſtly be taxed for it.</item>
                  <item>(4.) Whereas they ſay, If they loſe, they loſe but their own, I muſt deny it till they have made Even with their many Creditors. And till this be done, the ruin of theſe Gentlemen will be like the falling of an <hi>Old rotten Oak,</hi> which in tumbling beats down a multitude of little Shrubs and Under-woods.</item>
                  <item>(5.) To ſay, <hi>The Revenues belonging to your City are very low,</hi> is a notorious Scandal. And 'tis ſufficiently known, that the <hi>Chamber</hi> hath frequently refuſed many Sums of Mony of late, though it hath been offer'd them at Four <hi>per Cent.</hi> Intereſt.</item>
                  <item>(6.) As for'your <hi>Raiſing the Fifteens,</hi> I doubt not but it will be ſufficiently juſtified: it having been the Cuſtom of the City to raiſe them for ſuch uſes time out of mind. And the Reaſon why they have not been raiſed for ſome Years, till of late, is, becauſe there was no occaſion for it: The Profits ariſing to the City from the Duty upon <hi>Coals, &amp;c.</hi> given by Act of Parliament, having been applied to this purpoſe from the time of the great Fire in 66, till the time when the <hi>Fifteens</hi> were rais'd.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Obſervator condemns your City for offering to <hi>Inſure for Ever; which</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is to ſpoil the whole Deſign.</hi> The Argument which he produceth to prove this, he tells us, was the <hi>great one that was uſed at the ſetling their Office, to ſhew the certainty of their Security, which could no otherwiſe have given ſatisfaction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If therefore I can but pull down this main Pillar, their whole <hi>Inſurance Office</hi> like a rotten Building falls about their ears. Therefore, (1.) The Argument which the Obſervator uſeth to prove, that the City cannot well Inſure for Ever, will as ſtrongly prove, that theſe Gentlemen that offer to Inſure for 31 Years, ſhould not be truſted with all the <hi>Praemiums</hi> for ſo many Years at once, but collect them yearly; which they themſelves will not approve of. For thus he argues; and I with him: <hi>No Security can be good where all the Profit is at firſt received, and the Loſs is uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and continues for Ever</hi> (ſaith he); 'Tis the ſame for <hi>Thirty one Years</hi> (ſay I). <hi>For the Loſs being uncertain, the Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity cannot be proportion'd. And where all the Profit is at firſt received,</hi> (as it will be if Men Inſure with them for 31 <hi>Years</hi>) <hi>there is no Intereſt obliged to take care of the Deſign ſo, as to pay a Loſs and Preſerve the Fund. So that whenever the Loſs happens greater than the Annual Rent of the Security, the Land muſt be divided and torn in Pieces to ſatisfie the Loſs.</hi> So that this Argument muſt be quitted, becauſe 'tis as ſtrong againſt their Inſuring for <hi>Thirty one Years,</hi> as againſt the <hi>Cities</hi> Inſuring <hi>for Ever.</hi> I know it may be replied in the <hi>Obſervator</hi>'s own words, that <hi>when Houſes are Inſured for no longer than</hi> 31 <hi>Years, the</hi> Praemium <hi>that will ariſe from the Reverſion, will engage theſe Private Gentlemen to raiſe Mony to pay the Loſſes and preſerve the Fund entire, though the Loſſes were greater than</hi> 10 <hi>Years Rent of the Fund.</hi> But let any man of common Senſe judge, whether theſe Gentlemen will have any reaſon to ſecure the Reverſion of ſuch a Project where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by 20000 Pounds (two Thirds of their Fund) is loſt at one clap. (2.) All the Profit is not received by the City at <hi>firſt;</hi> for the Intereſt of the <hi>Praemiums</hi> of the Houſes Inſured by the City will be an <hi>Annual</hi> Profit to it. (3.) 'Tis probable indeed, that the Loſs by one years Fire may be greater than the Annual Rent of theſe Gentlemens Fund, which is|but 1400 Pound; but 'tis very improbable it ſhould be greater than the Annual Rent of the Cities <hi>Original Fund,</hi> which is 5000 Pound, and that of the <hi>Additional</hi> Fund of the <hi>Praemiums</hi> too. (4.) If the Loſs ſhould be greater than the Annual Rent of the Cities Security, yet the City would have as much reaſon to take care to pay the Loſſes and preſerve their Fund entire, as theſe Gentlemen would have to raiſe Mony to Preſerve theirs, if the Loſs on their ſide ſhould be greater than the Annual Rent of their Security. For why will the <hi>Praemium</hi> that will ariſe from the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion</hi> engage them to do ſo, but becauſe they hope in the next 31 Years to make up their great Loſs? And ſure the City may as well hope to make up their Loſs in time too; for though when the City Inſures <hi>for Ever</hi> they have no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſions, yet the <hi>Praemiums</hi> for that Reaſon are proportionably greater than thoſe of theſe Private men, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently are equivalent to their preſent <hi>Praemiums,</hi> and their Reverſion too; and therefore the City will be as careful to raiſe Mony to preſerve their Fund entire, though the Loſs at preſent ſhould be greater than Ten years Rent of their Fund.</p>
            <p>But further he objects, <hi>Should men Inſure their Houſes for Ever, your Corporation would have greater occaſion for an Act of Reſtraint, than the Spiritual Corporations heretofore have had; For though the Church and Colledges by granting long Leaſes prejudiced their Succeſſors, they left them the Old Rent: But your Committee will not be ſo kind to your Succeſſors; for you would not only leave them without Reverſions, but entail a perpetual Charge and Loſs upon the Corporation.</hi> But I anſwer, If the Committee intended to put the <hi>Praemiums</hi> of the Houſes to be Inſured into their <hi>own Private Pockets,</hi> as the <hi>Prebends</hi> of <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Fellows</hi> of <hi>Colledges</hi> do, and theſe Private <hi>Inſurancers</hi> intend, this Objection had a great deal of weight in it: But ſeeing theſe <hi>Praemiums</hi> are to be ſetled as a further Fund for the Publick good, you will have no need of an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Reſtraint:</hi> Neither indeed would they, if they had beſtowed the Profits of thoſe long Leaſes which they gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the preſent and future Publick good of thoſe Churches and Colledges to which they belonged; for had they done ſo, this would not have been for the Prejudice, but Advantage of their Succeſſors. 'Tis true, you leave your Succeſſors without <hi>Reverſions,</hi> if you Inſure <hi>for Ever;</hi> but then the <hi>Praemiums</hi> you receive from the Inſured are ſet proportionably the higher for it, which will be tranſmitted entire to thoſe that come after you; and ſo you will in all probability entail a perpetual Profit and Advantage (not a perpetual Charge and Loſs) upon the Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>The Fourth and Laſt Article upon which you are impeach'd, is, <hi>Your going to Council, to know whether you can ſettle your Ground-Rents.</hi> I foreſee this Objection will not go very far, becauſe it <hi>limps</hi> ſo fouly at its firſt ſetting out, there being not one ſyllable of this in any of your Papers; nor can it be drawn by any juſt conſequence from any of them. For your <hi>Tenth Propoſal</hi> (in which <hi>alone</hi> there is mention made of your Adviſing with Council) runs thus, That <hi>the ſaid Committee, in order to the ſaid Security, do forthwith by Advice of Council proceed to prepare Settlements of the ſaid Lands and Ground-Rents, and to draw up Articles and Agreements at large in purſuance of theſe Heads, to be propoſed to ſuch as ſhall Inſure upon the ſame:</hi> which implies; That the Committee and Common-Council were already ſatisfied, that they could ſettle the Lands, and therefore your Committee were not order'd to attend Council, to know whether they could ſettle, or no.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:30325:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>But,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>You have not diſcover'd to the World, where the Lands and Grounds you propoſe do lie?</hi> As if any man of Senſe or Modeſty would queſtion whether the City had ſuch Lands, or no.</p>
            <p>Well, but he hath Four Arguments to prove, that though you have them, yet they cannot be <hi>ſetled for the benefit of Private Perſons, ſo as to ſatisfie their Loſſes.</hi> (1.) <hi>The Lands of Corporations are generally charg'd for Publick and Special <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes, ſuch as repairing Bridges, maintaining Aqueducts, and ſupporting other Publick Works.</hi> I anſwer, That <hi>London-Bridge</hi> doth not only maintain it ſelf out of thoſe Lands that were granted, and are wholly applied to the Repairing of it, and thoſe Duties which are paid upon that account, but brings in a conſiderable <hi>Overplus</hi> too. And the <hi>Aqueducts</hi> and other <hi>Publick Works</hi> have been conſtantly maintained and ſupported, time out of mind, by raiſing the <hi>Fifteens:</hi> So that thoſe Ground-Rents and Lands which you ſet out for a Fund, are not appropriated and charged with any other Uſes at all. Though, if we conſider the condition of theſe Private Inſurancers, there's too much reaſon to fear, that there are ſome dormant <hi>Mortgages</hi> on thoſe Lands and Ground-Rents which they have ſetled for a Fund.</p>
            <p>His Second and Third Arguments I ſhall joyn together. <hi>How</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſhall Private men make the City willing, or force them to pay the Loſſes which may happen; For when a Diſpute ariſeth, the City may be made a Party. Now no Decree in that caſe can be made in</hi> Chancery, <hi>unleſs they appear; which, if they refuſe to do, they forfeit their Iſſues, which goes to the King, and ſo the Party cannot proceed in his Suit.</hi> I Anſwer, I cannot ſee how the City ſhould be made a Party, and ſo be ſummon'd to appear, when they have conveyed their whole Intereſt to the Truſtees, for the Security of ſuch as ſhall Inſure: But, if the City ſhould be made a Party, and refuſe to appear, they will not only forfeit their Iſſues, but the Sheriffs will be ſeverely Fined too; which Fine will be laid upon them higher and higher every Refuſal, ſo that the City will quickly be forced to Appear. <hi>But</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſome Perſons formerly lent Mony to the Chamber, and have Bond under the City Seal for their Payment; but yet could never recover their Debts. And how can it be expected that the Inſured ſhall have better Justice, when a great Loſs happens, than thoſe Perſons have had? And what if thoſe Creditors ſhould recover their Debts of the City, would they not ſeize theſe Ground-Rents that are now propoſed for your Fund?</hi> To anſwer this, I muſt give you a ſhort account of this matter, which is as follows: <hi>An.</hi> 1641. Sir <hi>Richard Gurny</hi> the <hi>Lord Mayor</hi> was by the Parliament ſent to the <hi>Tower,</hi> and divers other <hi>Aldermen</hi> were Turn'd out, Impriſon'd and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtred, becauſe they favour'd not the Deſigns of that Parliament in thoſe Times. Some time after Perſons of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Stamp got into their Places; And then the Common Council did, by the Order of the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage the City Seal for the payment of ſome Moneys advanced upon the <hi>Publick Faith</hi> (as it was then termed) for the carrying on of the unnatural Civil Wars of thoſe Times. But not one Penny of thoſe Moneys was ever paid into the <hi>Chamber,</hi> but Treaſurers for that purpoſe were Appointed by the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons,</hi> and it was all diſpoſed of by the Order of the ſaid Houſe. And for payment of that Mony, that Houſe did engage the <hi>Publick Faith,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward made an <hi>Ordinance,</hi> That thoſe that would double their Sum (before paid) ſhould be compenſated out of the Sequeſtred Eſtates, as many of them were. Now they that were not paid, have Sued the City ſince his Majeſties Reſtauration; but were not able to recover the ſame. But now this Fund will be ſetled in a time of <hi>Perfect Peace,</hi> under the <hi>Eſtabliſhed Government</hi> of the Kingdom, by the unanimous Conſent of a <hi>Common Council <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> choſen (ſo that there can never be any colour to pretend, that this buſineſs is driven on by a <hi>particular Powerful Party,</hi> as there is, that the other was; becauſe <hi>then</hi> the Government was under a Force.) As to what he ſaith, That it would be <hi>honourable and juſt for the City to ſell ſuch Lands as they can diſpoſe of, to pay thoſe Debts.</hi> I reply, Why ſhould they repay that Mony that was procured in ſo ill a manner. I think it would be very honourable and juſt if <hi>this Obſervator</hi> would pay thoſe <hi>Debts</hi> which he hath fairly contracted, and have been applied to his proper Benefit (as the other was not to the City's:) For then multitudes of Poor men and their Families would be relieved, who not being paid for their Work which he ſet them about; have their Mouths <hi>full</hi> (not of <hi>Bread</hi>) but of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints,</hi> and have little elſe to <hi>Drink,</hi> beſides their own <hi>Tears.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Fourth and Laſt Argument is this, <hi>What will become of your Settlement, if you forfeit your Charter? Whether the Lands of the Corporation do not then devolve on the Crown? Who then ſhall ſatisfie Loſſes and extinguiſh Fires?</hi> I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, What if the <hi>Sky</hi> ſhould <hi>fall;</hi> what a loſs would thoſe have, that have bought <hi>Nets</hi> for the <hi>catching of L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>k?</hi> But ſuppoſe the <hi>Charter</hi> ſhould be taken away (which God forbid) and the <hi>Corporation</hi> be diſſolved, always by Law thoſe Lands that have been purchaſed in the Name of the Corporation, do not go to the Crown, but return to the <hi>Perſons</hi> (or their <hi>Heirs</hi>) of whom they were at firſt purchaſed. Yet if theſe Lands are ſetled before-hand upon Private men, as Truſtees for Inſuring, they cannot devolve upon either, or be alienated from that Uſe.</p>
            <p>Thus, Sir, I think I have fully Anſwered this Pamphlet, and upon the Review find nothing more worth the taking notice of, unleſs it be thoſe <hi>ſcandalous</hi> Suggeſtions, that <hi>Your Committee are guilty of Raſhneſs, and want of Knowledge:</hi> And, that <hi>You have a regard more to your own Private Advantage, to procure certain Places for your ſelves, than the Publick Intereſt of the City.</hi> Were this later ſo, they might <hi>truly</hi> ſay, that <hi>this</hi> were an <hi>Imitation of their Pattern:</hi> But thoſe that know the largeneſs of your Underſtandings or Eſtates, will ſufficiently acquit you from both of thoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches; which indeed deſerve to be Anſwered rather by an <hi>Action</hi> of <hi>Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>der,</hi> than by the <hi>Pen</hi> of him, who is.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>HONOURED SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt humble Faithful Servant, <hi>L. R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
